And so we just had some very interesting משניות Mishnayot about the
basic parameters of פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen
discussing first of all how much the five shekel how much is
that worth in contemporary coinage and also in particular question about like
we spoke I think very interesting conceptual question about the relationship between
the ritual of פדיון Pidyon and the debt of פדיון. Pidyon. Our
מסכת Masechet is consistently made clear that without the debt of פדיון
Pidyon without the ability to demand it in court or whatever there's
no מצוה Mitzvah of פדיון הבן. Pidyon HaBen. It doesn't exist as
a ritual by itself without the underlying debt. And but then the
question is later on top of that there might be certain parameters
relating to the ritual like what the money is paid in. It
can't be paid with קרקע. Karka. It can't be paid you know
with real estate with slaves with שטרות Shtarot with IOUs and so
on. Fine that's when it's actually paid but still there's this underlying
basis the sense of the debt. So for example you have the
idea that if the father and the son die the estate is
still obligated and so on. All of that emerged pretty clearly and
even the גמרא Gemara had a case where what do you call
it where a person gave the money back and then he was
concerned that the next person wasn't giving it with a full heart
and therefore said that it was not legitimate because if that's the
debt then fundamentally it really has to be given with the full
intent of payment. So we just pointed out that while that's very
consistent the גמרא Gemara in קידושין Kiddushin talks about the possibility of
מתנה על מנת להחזיר Matana Al Menat Lehachzir
which would certainly indicate that it is there's an element of it
that can exist independent of the debt to divorce the ritual aspect
of it from the debt aspect of it. So that's one important
concept. I'm just saying this to wrap up because in today's משנה
Mishnah we're going to move beyond פדיון הבן Pidyon HaBen and the
other important concept that we had seen was the question about the
father's מצוה Mitzvah versus the son's מצוה. Mitzvah. If it's a choice
between the two who comes first and while in our משנה Mishnah
it seems like a debate whether the father primary obligation was to
the son or primary obligation is a person to himself and it
seems like the גמרא Gemara there tried to reframe it in saying
that if it's between you and your son all things being equal
actually you come first. I should mention that a number of later
אחרונים Acharonim and פוסקים Poskim or whatever you know
sort of while acknowledging our גמרא Gemara don't say that that conceptually
speaks really addresses the priorities and for example I've been meaning to
say this the מנחת חינוך Minchat Chinuch says let's say you haven't
been redeemed and it's you and your son and let's say now
but your son's an adult okay so you need to redeem now
who so he says who has the מצוה Mitzvah to redeem to
redeem my son me or my son my son's an adult he
can do it himself and he actually says that my מצוה Mitzvah
to redeem my adult son comes before my adult son's מצוה Mitzvah
to redeem it and if he chooses to redeem himself rather than
let me redeem it he's stolen a מצוה Mitzvah from me. So
I just bring that out to illustrate that against what our גמרא
Gemara sounded like the simple explanation is in the earlier sources and
you know even some אחרונים Acharonim emphasize this that the son's obligation
is only derived from the father the primary obligation is not on
the son the primary is on the father. So that's some summary
statement about פדיון הבן. Pidyon HaBen. We now turn our משנה Mishnah
to the question about the בכור Bechor for inheritance.
This is redundant really are we going to come back?
We have no we have one more משנה Mishnah פדיון הבן Pidyon
HaBen then we go on we have about בכור Bechor which is
for inheritance and then we go on to מעשר. Ma'aser.
What about things like the whole ritual that we do now like
you know the ברכה? Bracha? Yeah some of that develops post the
גמרא Gemara some of the ברכות Brachot are you know the גמרא
Gemara yeah the גמרא Gemara does not always you might be surprised
always speak about all the ritual that's around certain things but yes
some of those ברכות Brachot and some of whatever some is you
know some of that is post גמרא Gemara some of that is
in the גמרא Gemara and so on. And the גמרא Gemara isn't
even clearly conclude if it was day 30 or 31 did it?
No the גמרא Gemara doesn't conclude about a lot of things. So
what do we do? You have to do with later פוסקים Poskim
about it. So no we definitely hold you wait until after 30
days the only question is whether you can do 30 24-hour days
or it has to be after 30 Halachic days but I'm not
going into all those details okay if we were learning הלכות פדיון
הבן Hilchot Pidyon HaBen but that's what the גמרא Gemara our גמרא
Gemara has to say about it. There are one or two other
גמרות Gemarot scattered elsewhere in ש"ס Shas and now we're going to
turn on to the issue about the
firstborn for inheritance which somewhat by the way ties into this week's
פרשה Parsha because ראובן Reuven gets passed over for the whatever and
this week's פרשה Parsha opens with יעקב Yaakov giving a double portion
to יוסף. Yosef. So let's take a look at the issue about
the double portion. משנה Mishnah at the bottom of נ"א עמוד ב'.
Nun Aleph Amud Bet. בכור נוטל פי שנים בנכסי האב ואינו נוטל
פי שנים בנכסי האם. Bechor Notel Pi Shenayim Benichsei Ha'av Ve'eino Notel
Pi Shenayim Benichsei Ha'em. So the firstborn gets a double portion in
the father's estate and not in the mother's estate. Now the simple
explanation of this means that if let's say a mother dies now
if a mother dies then her husband inherits her but let's say
her husband's also dead so let's say oh let's say let's say
the husband dies first and everybody inherited him and then the mother
dies so now the sons are going to inherit her. So when
the sons inherit their mother then they don't get a double portion
this firstborn doesn't get a double portion whether it's her firstborn whether
it's his firstborn it doesn't matter it's only for the father's estate
not for the mother's estate. Now that's the simple The משנה. Mishnah.
רש״י Rashi says, you know what, I'll, well, okay, I'll say it
very briefly, I don't want to skip this, רש״י Rashi says what
we're talking about is the dowry, the נכסי מלוג Nichsei Melog that
the wife brought into the marriage. So, but the רש״ש Rashash doesn't
understand what רש״י Rashi is talking about because he says look, the
dowry that the wife brings into the marriage, if she dies first,
the husband inherits her. So then it's no different than if he
inherited money, you know, if he bought property, any money under his
control that he fully owns when he dies, pass on to his
sons. If the father, if that's if the mother died first. If
the father dies first, then it reverts to the mother. So what's
רש״י's Rashi's scenario about the son getting the נכסי מלוג Nichsei Melog
of the mother? So I just point that out that I actually
think there is an answer to that, but for now I'm going
to bracket that. The simple sense of the משנה Mishnah is father
dies first, firstborn and everybody inherits, then the then the mother has
her own property, she gets back her dowry, she has her own
property, she dies, and now so now she's getting her כתובה Kesubah
back, right? Or not? Not the, well, yes, she does get the
200 זוז Zuz of the כתובה, Kesubah, but I'm talking about the
dowry that she brought in. If she brought property into the marriage,
then she takes it back out when the husband dies. Okay, so
now the husband dies and the צאן ברזל, Tzon Barzel, which is
both נכסי מלוג Nichsei Melog and צאן ברזל, Tzon Barzel, they're figured
differently, and then she dies. So now she dies and her sons
inherit her, they do not get פי שנים. Pi Shenayim. So they
divide it equally. They divide it equally. And she she takes out
before the sons get from the father. Yes, when the when the
father dies, she does not inherit her husband, but she does take
out, first of all, she gets her כתובה Kesubah payment, her 200
זוז, Zuz, but in addition to her כתובה Kesubah payment, she gets
back any money that she brought in in the dowry. Okay, so
and so anyway, and then she might just on her own be
invested in the stock market and be a millionaire and who knows
what. Anyway, she dies, if her husband isn't alive, her sons inherit
her, but they do not get, the firstborn does not get פי
שנים. Pi Shenayim. Okay, ואינו נוטל בשבח ולא בראוי כבמוחזק. Ve'eino notel
beshevach velo beraui kev'muchzak. Now, when the firstborn gets the double, he
does not get in the amount the estate improved. Father died and
he left a field. Now, first of all, I should say a
word about how do you figure out the double portion. Let's say
there are three brothers. What's the double portion? It can't be two-thirds,
right? That's not exactly double, that's much much more than anybody else
is getting. So what you do is you add a portion, so
you divide the field or the estate not into three but into
four, and he gets two quarters and the other brother gets one
quarter. Is that clear? So basically the way you figure out the
double portion is you assume there's an additional brother, okay, and you
divide it that many times and he gets that additional brother's part.
So if you have three brothers, you you divide the field by
four, he gets two-fourths, they each get a fourth. Now, so we
have this field, he's going to get half of it, the other
two brothers are going to get a quarter. And now after the
father died, they struck oil. Okay, or now after the, well actually
that's maybe not as relevant because maybe the oil was always always
there. After they died, they harvested the wheat. After they died, the
fruits ripened. They after they after the father died, they, you know,
they they planted the crops and they harvested the crops and all
of this before they it came time to split it up. He
does not get double in that. He only gets double in the
amount that was around when the father died. Any amount of improvement
afterwards is divided equally between the brothers. Okay, so that's the שבח.
Shevach. ראוי Raui is a similar concept, it's stuff that comes after,
but it's not the physical improvement of the field, it's stuff that
is would is coming to him from outside sources. To one the
the the most obvious example about this is an inheritance. After the
father dies, then his brother died or the grandfather died.
Okay, so therefore now that grandfather dies, what happens if the grandfather
dies? So it goes to the son. I mean, it, you know,
the father's father would go to his son, the son isn't alive.
So it goes to his son's children. Okay, so those sons children
get, but they are not, but even though that in conceptually is
passing into their father's estate and from their father's estate being divided
by them, they're not getting it directly as heirs. The way you
know they're not getting it directly as heirs is let's say the
grandfather who died had two children. Okay, one is alive and the
other is dead and he has five kids. How do you divide
it? Half goes to the one that's alive, the other half goes
to the five kids, the five grandkids, because basically it's going to,
I'm ignoring the בכור. Bechor.
Okay, fine, let's not make things confusing. That half goes to the
dead father and the dead father as an equal brother and then
it gets divided. divide by his kids. So conceptually that's going into
the dead father's estate and then being divided.
Nevertheless, because it wasn't around when the father died, it only came
afterwards, it's only ראוי, ra'uy, fit to be coming to the father,
but never actually came to the father when the father was alive.
Therefore, it is divided—they do not, the בכור bechor does not get
a double portion. Now, that's a case of inheritance. תוספות Tosfos raises,
a lot of these big תוספותים Tosfsim are focused on one major
question, and that is the status of a מלווה, milveh, a loan.
Because, and everyone knows about middle ages and the joys, right? Jews
made a lot of money by lending money. So, they were excluded
from a lot of other endeavors, you know, from the trades and
from the and from crop and from real estate, so they were
limited to lending money. And of course, you know, then whatever we
suffered because of how we got stereotyped as a result, that's a
different story. Anyway, Jews were into lending, you know, that was a
major source of their economy. Now, what happens תוספות Tosfos says, if
the father has outstanding loans? Okay? You know, somebody owes me a
million dollars, a hundred thousand dollars. Is that ראוי? ra'uy? I mean,
it's right now owed to him. It's not like the case of
inheritance where right now I have no relationship to my, you know,
to the grandfather's estate or whatever, his father's father's estate. This is
something that is directly owed to him, but it is not yet
under his control. Maybe he even has liens on somebody else's estate,
so he has something real, but it's not yet in his hands.
תוספות Tosfos anyway concludes that loans are considered to be ראוי, ra'uy,
not מוחזק, muchzak, and that's a very big implication that loans that
are paid after death, the בכור bechor does not get a double
portion on them. Okay, so that is the principle that you do
not get in the שבח, shevach, in the what it improved, and
not in the ראוי, ra'uy, not in what is fit to come
to you. כבמוחזק, kebemuchzak, you do not get in it as if
you were already in possession of it. The בכור bechor only gets
a double portion of the things that he is in possession of.
Okay, does anyone disagree with תוספות? Tosfos? What? Does anyone disagree with
תוספות? Tosfos? Well, if you take a look at the first line,
ולא בראוי כבמוחזק, velo bera'uy kebemuchzak, he says בפרק יש נוחלין פסקינן
הלכתא דאין הבכור נוטל פי שנים במלווה, bePerek Yesh Nochalim paskinan hilchasa
de'ein habechor notel pi shnayim bemilveh, בין שגבו קרקע בין שגבו מעות.
bein shegavsu karka bein shegavsu ma'os. Okay, and then he discusses other
types of cases. So basically it's a discussion in בבא בתרא, Bava
Basra, and, you know, and the clear conclusion is that a מלווה
milveh is considered ראוי. ra'uy. All right? Because he talks about other
issues about כתובת אשה, kesuvas isha, and is כתובת אשה kesuvas isha
similar to מלווה milveh or not similar to מלווה milveh and other
types of implications. So I really actually slightly misstated it because תוספות's
Tosfos larger discussion is not about מלווה, milveh, that's a pretty clear
conclusion from the גמרא Gemara in בבא בתרא. Bava Basra. But he's
still very concerned about מלווה-related milveh issues. Okay, now, top of נז
עמוד א, Nun-Zayin amud Alef, ולא האשה בכתובתה. velo ha'isha bekesuvatah. And
a woman who is collecting her כתובה, kesuvah, right? The husband died
and now she can collect her כתובה kesuvah from the husband's estate,
whether it's in the possession of the יורשים yorshim or whether it
is in the possession of people that purchased the estate, she's got
a lien on the estate, right? She's like any other creditor. Any
other creditor, you lend money to me, I have a lien on
your property. Okay, so that person sells his property to somebody else,
I can collect it from somebody else after the lien exists. The
person dies, I can collect it from the יורשים, yorshim, okay? There
are certain maybe limits and different הלכות halachos by יורשים, yorshim, but
for now we'll assume it's the same. Anyway, so the husband dies,
the woman can collect from her lien from the יורשים yorshim and
from the and from the people who purchased the property. But, but
she cannot collect, what can she not collect? She cannot collect if
the property improved afterwards, or if the estate, her dead husband's estate,
if that got property afterwards. Okay, meaning, so she had a lien
on her husband's estate, what? She had a lien on the estate,
her כתובה kesuvah was worth I don't know, ten thousand dollars. There's
only five thousand dollars in the estate. But then the dead husband's
father dies and now there's ten thousand dollars in the estate. She
can't collect it. It was not around at the time when the
husband died. Or, there's five thousand in the estate, but the son
somehow sold off five thousand to other people. Okay, excuse me. There's
five thousand in the estate, and then however, they improved it and
they built on it and they planted and they harvested and now
it's worth ten thousand. Okay, she can't collect ten thousand, she can
only collect the amount that it was worth when the husband died.
Okay, that's ולא האשה בכתובתה, velo ha'isha bekesuvatah, yes. I forget the
categories, but there's a category where she when they first marry and
she brings in her dowry, yeah, but her dowry is what? נכסי
מלוג? nichsei milug? Her property that she has, like real estate... Right,
yes. It could be real estate, it could be chattel, but yes.
And then she gets that back plus her כתובה. kesuvah. Plus her
כתובה, kesuvah, right. So here we're not talking about her getting back
the property she brought in. Okay, we're talking about her getting her
basic כתובה kesuvah payment of like the 200 זוז zuz or whatever,
the תוספת tosefes and so on. That's a good question. That is
considered because the stuff that's נכסי מלוג nichsei milog is stuff she
always retained title to. So there it's not a question about where
she's going to get it from, she always retained the title of
that. The נכסי צאן ברזל, nichsei tzon barzel, which is a less
common category, which we completely transfer the title to the husband, and
then she's entitled after the death to take out the value that
they were worth at the time when they got married. So that
really does become an outstanding debt, meaning the title totally transferred, right?
And then we estimated their value, they were worth $5,000 when we
got married, so now I owe my wife $5,000, but she doesn't
have title to the things she brought in. So whether the נכסי
צאן ברזל nichsei tzon barzel would have the same הלכה halacha as
the כתובה, ketubah, that's an interesting question. In נכסי מלוג, nichsei milog,
she just as I said takes, you know, it's the same property
she takes out. Whether those also would be limited, they might be,
because that's also, that's also a debt, but it's a different debt.
It's a debt that began at the moment of marriage as opposed
to the debt of the כתובה, ketubah, which only begins when the
husband dies or divorces her. So it's not clear, I'd have to
check. It's an interesting question. What's the difference between the two again?
נכסי מלוג nichsei milog is she retains title, okay? נכסי מלוג nichsei
milog is basically I have, I don't know, a vineyard and a
wheat field. Okay, let's say my wheat field is נכסי מלוג nichsei
milog and my vineyard is נכסי צאן ברזל. nichsei tzon barzel. So
the נכסי מלוג, nichsei milog, I retain title to the wheat field.
I, the husband, I, the woman, okay, I'm sorry, I'm the woman.
I retain title to the wheat field. My husband gets to harvest
it and sell the wheat every year and he gets the use
of it, but I retain title. So when he dies, so he
gets the produce, so when he, so he's not allowed, there's a
whole question about what if he tried to sell it, but let's
assume he doesn't, he's not allowed to sell it. So when he
dies, I just retake possession of that, end of story, I retain
title of it. No matter what condition it's in. Right. But the
vineyard, we determine what it's worth when we get married. It's worth
$5,000. It's now totally his. He can do whatever he wants with
the vineyard. Okay, and now when he dies, I just get entitled
to the $5,000 of what it was worth when we got married.
Okay, so that, you're right, is a debt, but it's a different
type of a debt than the כתובה. ketubah. It was basically incurred
from the moment of marriage and it's not clear to me it
would follow the same הלכה, halacha, so I'd have to check, I
don't know. And about when she receives that, it's not clear. Well,
she does, she receives it at death or divorce, that's true. But
whether it's limited, but the debt was incurred at the moment of
marriage. Okay, so anyway, there the כתובה ketubah debt is not as
clear because the כתובה ketubah debt won't even come into force if
she dies before him. You know what I mean? So the כתובה
ketubah debt is really in the eventuality of death or divorce. But
anyway, for the נכסי צאן ברזל, nichsei tzon barzel, it's not clear
to me if it follows the same. That's basically her taking out
what she brought in. The כתובה ketubah is more the new debt
incurred by the כתובה. ketubah. Okay, so whether it has the same
limitations is not clear to me. Okay, so when the woman is
coming to collect her כתובה, ketubah, she can only do it from
the property that was in the estate at the time of the
death. So with the כתובה, ketubah, we're assuming it's going to be
the 200 זוז zuz and any תוספת. tosefet. That she can only
collect from the property that was there at the time of the
death, not property that the estate got afterwards or not the amount
that the estate improved afterwards. Okay, and we'll ask in the גמרא
Gemara why that is, because logically that doesn't make so much sense.
Let's keep on going. ולא בנות במזונותיהם. V'lo banot b'mezonoteihem. The daughters
also, when they collect, when they're being paid for their support, their
sustenance, they can only collect it from the estate at the time
of death. What does that mean, the sustenance of the daughters? רש״י
Rashi says the case is that a man married a woman who
already had children, so he took on some stepdaughters, and therefore he
agreed, he doesn't have to, but he stipulated with his new wife
that he would pay their support for five years, ten years, whatever
the case might be. And in that type of a case, and
then he dies, where can they collect that from, which part of
the estate? Now תוספות Tosafot says, first of all, that's wrong for
a couple of reasons. Number one, that you wouldn't have just said
בנות, banot, you would have said בנים banim or בנות, banot, so
there's no reason it was limited to daughters. When the גמרא Gemara
talks about that, it doesn't talk only about daughters. Number one. Number
two is, that's totally an independently contracted debt, and an independently contracted
debt, then if somebody has a lien against you as a creditor,
they're entitled to seize the property if it improves after the fact,
okay? And we'll talk about that in the גמרא. Gemara. So that
would not have this limitation. That would be an independently contracted debt
and we wouldn't have even mentioned daughters in particular. תוספות Tosafot says
what we're talking about is a standard כתובה ketubah obligation. גמרא Gemara
will make it clear that this is talking about a standard כתובה
ketubah obligation. What is a standard כתובה ketubah obligation relating to the
daughters? It is the following: if the father dies and the daughters
are, you know, left without somebody to provide for them, right, so
you know, their mother has her כתובה ketubah money, their brothers get
their estate, what do they get? Only if they have to live
off of the charity of their mother and their brothers? So no.
So what the standard obligation in the כתובה ketubah that is, you
really don't have a choice about, that חז״ל Chazal instituted. Was that
they are entitled to get support from the estate in terms of
basically room and board until they get married. Okay, so they are,
which by the way reflects the גמרא, Gemara, until they get married.
What happens if they're actually... is it limited to a certain age?
I'd have to check. If they're already, you know, 15, 18 when
the father died, they never get married, they can basically live on
the estate? Yeah, I mean, the תנאי Tnai is עד דתנסבין לגוברין,
Ad detinsavin legavrin, but I'm trying to remember if there's any limit
on that. That's a good question. I'll have to double-check. Okay, anyway,
so that type of thing, that they are supported by the estate
until they get married, which also, by the way, just reflects the
reality, right? Is that basically the economic reality was you assumed that
women are not going to be wage earners, they're only supported through
men. So the father supports until they get married and then the
husband supports. So as opposed to the sons that actually got an
actual estate, right, the daughters actually just get support till their responsibility
can be taken over by the husbands. That reflects those social-economic realities
of that time. Actually, later there was an institution that actually did
give them a portion of the inheritance, at least like equal to
half of that of the sons, but anyway, we're not going there.
So that idea that they are supported by the estate, since that
is something that חז״ל Chazal imposed and is a special obligation the
father really doesn't have any say about it, they can only be
supported by the amount of the estate that exists at the time
of the father's death. If, for example, the estate money run out
and the only reason now there's additional funds in the estate is
because more money came in after the death, either the property improved,
again, שבח, Shevach, or ראוי, Ra'uy, or the dead father inherited from
his father, whatever the case might be, they're not entitled to those
additional funds that come in after the father's death. Yes, question. And
that's a natural obligation for stepchildren? Correct. These aren't even stepchildren. רש״י
Rashi talks about stepchildren. רש״י Rashi says no obligation for stepchildren. Those
are basically the responsibility of the father or whoever, exactly. Okay, so
this responsibility... but that's רש״י, Rashi, תוספות Tosafot rejects it. תוספות Tosafot
says absolutely the clear פשט Pshat of this משנה Mishnah is the
general responsibility of a person to provide for his daughters or the
estate to provide for the daughters even after his death. Okay. הלאה,
Hala, יבם. Yavam. Now, how about the brother-in-law? The brother-in-law, what's the
story with the brother-in-law? If a brother-in-law does יבום Yibum to his
sister-in-law, his dead brother's wife, his brother died with no kids, so
the פסוק Pasuk says יקום על שם אחיו המת, Yakum al shem
achiv hamet, he will stand up in the place of his dead
brother. So what חז״ל Chazal say that means is, if he's standing
up in the place of his dead brother, then he gets his
dead brother's portion in the estate. So there's a very... if he's
also the בכור, Bechor, yes, but when the dead brother was a
בכור, Bechor, and he gets the double portion of the dead brother
plus his own, so the יבם Yavam now gets three portions? If
the dead brother is a בכור, Bechor, does he also get the
בכור Bechor portion? Nice question. Man, okay, a lot of things I'll
have to get back to you about here. Been a while since
I did בבא בתרא Bava Batra or יבמות, Yevamot, so I'll have
to get back to you about that. That's a very interesting question.
Okay, if he is the בכור, Bechor, then yes, he gets three
portions, his own two plus one. That's interesting though, whether he would
also get the בכור Bechor portion. Anyway, he gets his... I'm sure
it's מפורש, Meforash, I just can't remember. Anyway, so he gets his
dead brother's portion, which by the way is a nice additional incentive
to do יבום. Yibum. So, you know, the גמרא Gemara was afraid
that people were going to do יבום... Yibum... there's a whole question
about whether יבום Yibum comes first or חליצה Chalitzah does first. And
it says, well, יבום Yibum should come first, well, maybe חליצה Chalitzah
should come first nowadays because people will do יבום Yibum because, you
know, the woman is very attractive or whatever, they're not doing it
לשם מצוה. Leshem mitzvah. Well, there's another reason they might be doing
it also. You get a whole portion of the estate if it's
a very wealthy estate. Anyway, if he does that, if he does
get that extra portion, and if the estate improved, again, after the
father died, and we'll discuss when he did the יבום Yibum or
whatever, but later improvements of the estate don't... he does not get
his dead brother's portion of those later improvements. That is divided equally
between him and the surviving brothers. Okay, so it is not... he
doesn't get a double portion, his and his dead brother's, for those
improvements afterwards. And then it just repeats the point, וכולם, Vekulam, all
the people we just mentioned, אינו נוטלים בשבח ולא בראוי כבמוחזק, Eino
notlim beshevach velo bera'uy kevamucheshak, do not get in the amount that
the field improved and do not get in funds that come into
the estate. So the גמרא Gemara will say. Let's take a look
now, very tight משנה, Mishnah, a lot packed in, it took us
a half hour just to get through that, but anyway, the גמרא
Gemara should go very quickly now that we've understood those principles. Yes,
so you just said that this brother who does יבום, Yibum, he
gets his portion plus his dead brother's portion. Right. Only question is
whether if the dead brother was a בכור, Bechor, whether he got
the בכור Bechor portion. Right, right, right. Let's take a look. Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara says like this: מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? So
let's start from the beginning. Why does he not get from his
mother's estate? Why only from his father's? אמר קרא: Amar Kra: ולו
משפט הבכורה לו, Velo mishpat habechora lo, the פשט pshat of the
פסוק pasuk is talking about the firstborn, he's entitled to the double
portion, you can't give it to another kid. That's פשט pshat of
the פסוק. pasuk. But the גמרא Gemara reads 'לו' lo the father,
to the father is the laws of בכורה. bechora. Okay. What was
that? ולו משפט הבכורה, Velo mishpat habechora, right? What was it? ולו
משפט הבכורה. Velo mishpat habechora. לא יוכל לבכר את בן האהובה על
פני בן השנואה הבכור כי את הבכור בן השנואה יכיר לתת לו
פי שנים בכל אשר ימצא לו כי הוא ראשית אנו לו משפט
הבכורה. Lo yuchal levaker et ben ha'ahuva al pnei ben hasnu'a habechor,
ki et habechor ben hasnu'a yakir latet lo pi shnayim bechol asher
yimatze lo, ki hu reshit ono, lo mishpat habechora. Are you right?
Probably. I'll trust you on that. Anyway, either way, משפט הבכורה לאיש
ואין משפט הבכורה לאשה. mishpat habechora le'ish ve'ein mishpat habechora le'isha. They're
referring to the they're reading the 'לו' lo referring to the father,
for the father is the laws of the firstborn, not for the
mother. The mother's kids when the father is already dead only get
do there's no double portion. Wait, wait, wait. ולו משפט הבכורה Velo
mishpat habechora is somehow saying that it's going on the father, not
the mother? Well, no, yeah, כי הוא ראשית אנו, ki hu reshit
ono, right? There's two people being referred to here. What do they
call the pronouns, the antecedents? כי הוא, Ki hu, he, the בכור,
bechor, is ראשית אנו, reshit ono, is his, the father's, firstborn. לו
משפט הבכורה. Lo mishpat habechora. Which 'לו'? lo So you would say
'לו' lo means the son. The בכור bechor has the right. But
the גמרא Gemara is reading it 'לו' lo the father, to the
father apply the laws of בכורה, bechora, not to the mother. Okay.
So, okay. ואין משפט הבכורה לאשה. Ve'ein mishpat habechora le'isha. ואינו נוטל
בשבח. Ve'eino notel beshevach. How do you know the בכור bechor does
not get in improvements of the field? דכתיב: Dechtiv: בכל אשר ימצא
לו. Bechol asher yimatze lo. Everything that is found to him, meaning
everything that's in the estate when the father dies, but not that
comes in afterwards. Everything that is ימצא, yimatze, that is found there.
ולא בראוי כבמוחזק. Velo berauy kevemuchzak. You don't get about also things
that are coming in later. First of all, it's improvements of the
field, not coming later. Basically the same point. דכתיב: Dechtiv: בכל אשר
ימצא לו. Bechol asher yimatze lo. Fine. So that's the issue why
they're limited to things that come later. And now we go on
to there's just boop boop boop, we're dealing with all the cases
in the משנה. Mishna. ולא האשה בכתובתה. Velo ha'isha biksuvata. Now that's
about the בכור. bechor. How do you know about the woman collecting
כתובה? ketubah? ולא האשה בכתובתה. Velo ha'isha biksuvata. אין זה ראוי? Ein
zeh ra'uy? ואמר שמואל: Ve'amar Shmuel: בעל חוב גובה את השבח. Ba'al
chov goveh et hashevach. Let's say a woman with her כתובה ketubah
is basically just like a creditor. Games here not games, somebody else,
Reuven lent money to me, right? I have a thousand dollar debt
against Reuven. He dies. Okay. Or, you know, you could also talk
about, let's say he sold his land to somebody else. I have
a lien on that land. That land improves. I still have a
lien on that land and I can collect all the land including
improvements that occurred after the debt. I can get that to pay
my debt. Or I have a lien against Reuven's estate. He dies.
The land improves or other stuff come into the estate. I can
actually collect my debt from the stuff that came in later. Okay.
Now, you might ask why exactly is that true? Maybe my lien
should be limited to, you know, to what was available at the
time that the, you know, at the time of the lien or
whatever. But that's nevertheless the הלכה. halacha. תוספות Tosafot has a whole
discussion about, you know, why that's true. But that is the הלכה
halacha in general by a creditor. I'm entitled to take from the
heirs or from the purchasers if I have a lien on the
property. I'm entitled to take from it to pay up my full
debt. So why here is the woman limited? So the גמרא Gemara
says: אמר רבי אבא: Amar Rabbi Abba: מקולי כתובה שנו כאן. Mikulei
ketubah shanu kan. You're right. It's a special lenient thingy or, you
know, or limit to כתובה. ketubah. Meaning, yeah, you're right. There are
some times it's an interesting one when we learn כתובות Ketubot we
can talk about it. You know, there's some times that חז"ל Chazal
actually, you know, give special rights to the woman or the whole
institution of כתובה, ketubah, you know, was in order to make sure
that the woman was protected and make sure that fathers would want
to marry off their daughters. So there was a lot of things
that were done actually there that improved the woman's status. But on
the other hand, it's all a balancing act. If you, you know,
because then if it becomes too burdensome, then nobody's going to want
to get married or people I don't know. But anyway, it's a
balancing act of people's protecting people and, you know, on both sides
of the equation. Okay. So therefore, you know, or maybe people won't
want to buy fields from this guy because the wife has a
big outstanding כתובה. ketubah. I don't know. Whatever the case might be,
it's a balancing act. So there are times where we don't give
the כתובה ketubah the full weight of a normal debt. So here
we limit her to collecting from what was in the estate at
the time, not what improved afterwards. א קולא A kula meaning meaning
it alleviates some of the burden of the debt. Meaning it's א
קולא a kula for the debtor, not for her. Okay. Alleviates some
of the burden. ולא הבנות במזונותיהן. Velo habanot bimezonoteihen. Not the daughters
to pay for their... support. מאי טעמא, Mai ta'ama, what's the reason?
תנאי דכתובה דמי, Tenaich d'ketuvah dami, because that again is something that
the husband really, this is proof against רשי, Rashi, he had no
say in, it was imposed upon him by חזל Chazal that he
would have to support his daughters after he died, his estate would
have to support it. So therefore, you know, while on the one
hand we're imposing this obligation on this person, which is protecting the
interests of the daughters, but at the same time we want to
maybe also protect the interests of the sons to a certain degree,
so we're not going to give them unlimited, you know, rights. And
therefore, maybe it's like the rest of the כתובה ketuvah and they're
limited to what the estate was at the time of the death.
Okay. ולא הבנות במזונותיהן. V'lo habanos bimzonoteihem. I'm sorry, just did that.
Okay. ולא היבם, V'lo hayabam, not the יבם yabam when he gets
his dead brother's portion. מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? בכור קריה רחמנא, Bechor
kariya rachmana, the Torah called it בכור. bechor. Now why does the
Torah call it בכור? bechor? Because what the Torah says actually is,
because it says, והיה הבכור אשר תלד יקום על שם אחיו המת.
V'haya habechor asher teled yakum al shem achiv hamet. So again, the
פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk is that he now has married
his dead brother's wife. If he has a firstborn son, that son
somehow takes the place of the dead father. But the חזל Chazal
read it, הבכור אשר תלד, habechor asher teled, somehow they read that
what it means is that the one who chooses to marry this
wife is now like a בכור. bechor. And therefore he gets a
double portion. So seems like a definite stretch of the simple meaning
of the פסוק, pasuk, but anyway based on that reading, conceptually his
double portion is gives him a quasi-בכור bechor status. So his right
to that second portion are like a בכור's bechor rights and are
limited to what is in the estate at the time of the
death. Okay. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, now said אביי, Abaye, לא שנו
אלא בשבח ששבחו נכסים בין מיתה ליבום אבל בין יבום לחלוקה שקיל.
Lo shanu ela b'shevach sheshivchu nechasim bein mita l'yibum aval bein yibum
lachaluqa shakil. When is he limited to not get what comes after
the death? It's the improvement of the estate between the father's death
and just one second, just one second, hold on, hold on. Father's
death? Thank you. One minute, one minute, one minute. Okay. One minute,
just one second. Hold on a second, I just want to make
sure I'm saying this right. Just one second. Hold on a second.
בין מיתת אביהם ליבום. bein mitat avihem l'yibum. No, excuse me, not
the brother. Right, there's two people dying here. So I just wanted
to double check. Right. So the father died. Okay? So let's assume
the scenario is, right, because it's basically the improvement of the estate
after the death of the father that's of interest, right? That's the
whole question of ראוי, ra'uy, how much the estate improved after the
father's death. So here basically we're assuming he did יבום yibum when
the father was still alive, and then the father died. Okay? So
now, and then the estate improves. So he says, so if that
improvement he's not entitled to, the same way if he was a
בכור bechor after the father died, he would not be entitled to
the improvement. So now he took his brother's portion, then the father
died. So like a בכור, bechor, he gets what was in the
estate at the death of the father, but he does not get
what it improved afterwards. So לא שנו אלא בשבח ששבחו נכסים בין
מיתה Lo shanu ela b'shevach sheshivchu nechasim bein mita between the death
of the father ליבום l'yibum to the fact that he has done
the יבום. yibum. Oh, sorry, I did say it a little bit
wrong. Okay, right, I'm sorry. So what happened was the following. Right,
excuse me. The father died, but he hasn't yet done יבום. yibum.
Okay? So maybe his brother is already dead, maybe his brother died
after the father, it doesn't matter. He has yet to do יבום.
yibum. Okay? בין מיתה bein mita is the brother's death. The brother
dies and then the father dies. Why say hold on a second.
That's what I was thinking. One minute, one minute, one minute. Okay,
hold on, hold on. Yeah, hold on one second. I think you're
right. One minute. Hold on a second. בין מיתה ליבום. bein mita
l'yibum. Well either way it wouldn't matter whether it was the brother's
death or the father's death because we have to assume, it really
doesn't matter because really what he's saying is that it could be
either. I think from רשי Rashi it could be you're right that
it reads easier if it's referring to the brother's death, but it
really doesn't matter because really the point is is that the brother
dies, the father dies, he has yet to do יבום, yibum, okay,
so any improvement in the, the improvement of the estate that we're
interested in is the way it improved after the father's death. Okay.
The brother obviously is dead because it's waiting יבום. yibum. So I
don't think it really matters how you interpret. מיתה, misah, but the
point is when we're talking about the way the estate improved, it's
improved after the father's death, okay? So the basic point is you
could even bracket the word מיתה. misah. The basic point is that
any improvement of the estate, obviously the father's already dead or else
it's not a relevant conversation, so any improvement of the estate prior
to יבום, yibum, right? So we're both the father and the brother
are dead, so it's really both. Anyway, any improvement of the estate
prior to יבום, yibum, he's not entitled to a double portion, okay?
אבל דבין יבום לחלוקה, aval d'vein yibum l'chaluka, if he did יבום
yibum and then the estate improved, again the father's already dead, he
did יבום yibum and then the estate improved and they haven't divided
it, then he does get a double portion. Why? שקיל, shakil, he
does get. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? יקום על שם אחיו המת אמר
רחמנא והרי קם. yakum al shem achiv hames amar rachmana v'harei kam.
It says when he does יבום yibum he takes the brother's place
and he took the brother's place. Means what? So let's just imagine
this, okay? He did the act of יבום. yibum. Now he basically,
although we're basing it on the פסוק pasuk of בכור, bechor, conceptually
it's
really not בכור, bechor, conceptually what he is is he
represents himself and his dead brother. So let's imagine, right, that the
father died, okay, and then the field improved and then it came
time to divide it. All the brothers would equally divide the improvement
as well as the base cost, correct? So similar case, he did
יבום, yibum, he now represents himself and his brothers. So now the
field improved and they divided it, well fine, he now represents him
and his brother and he gets an equal double portion for the
improvement as well. Okay, in that way it's different than בכור. bechor.
The בכור bechor does not represent a brother, the בכור bechor just
is given a free extra portion. So even when it improves between
death and division, which is always the standard case, the case is
that it improves between the father's death and the division, the בכור
bechor doesn't get it. His bonus portion is limited to what it
was at the time of the father's death. But here, it's not
a bonus portion, here he now represents his brother. So once he
has done יבום yibum and is standing in for himself and he's
standing in for his brother, right, so now he should be entitled
to any improvement from the time he began to stand in for
his brother's place. Right. There's simply no בכור bechor here, he gets
two. Yes. So that's the point, okay? So again, however you explain
the word מיתה, misah, obviously both the father and his brother are
dead, but the basic point is that fine, he could be limited
until he does יבום, yibum, but once he does יבום yibum he
now represents his brother. Okay, let's just finish the answer. רבא אמר,
Rava amar, now רבא Rava says, אפילו דבין יבום לחלוקה נמי לא
שקיל. afilu d'vein yibum l'chaluka nami lo shakil. Even that improvement he
doesn't get. מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? בכור, bechor, because
it's like בכור, bechor, like we just said that his double portion
is partly learned out from the fact that he's like a בכור.
bechor. מה בכור אין לו קודם חלוקה אף יבם נמי אין לו
קודם חלוקה. ma bechor ein lo kodem chaluka af yavam nami ein
lo kodem chaluka. So רבא Rava says no, it's just like בכור.
bechor. So this becomes a fascinating conceptual question of how do we
think about the יבם's yavam double portion? Is the יבם's yavam double
portion because he represents his brother, which is the most logical thing
to say, or is his double portion to somehow once he's done
יבום yibum like it's like a bonus, like maybe the תורה Torah
said, oh, you're such a good guy, you did יבום, yibum, so
now we'll give you, we'll treat you like a בכור, bechor, which
might also be relevant to your question if the brother was entitled
to the בכור, bechor, okay? So is it a בכור bechor status
or is it his brother status? So the question is after he's
done יבום, yibum, if it's his brother status, he'd represent his brother,
any improvement now equally comes to him. But if it's a בכור
bechor status, then he's only going to get treated like a בכור
bechor will get treated and it goes to the estate at the
time of the father's death. So he could potentially be losing out
if there's like a lot of שבח shevach over there? Sure. I
mean like it could have been better off not having done יבום.
yibum. No, no, no. You always get extra. No, because I mean
let's say the שבח shevach is like five times. You always get
your שבח shevach for your own portion. Right, but you don't get
the שבח shevach for the brother's, the dead brother's portion. Of course
you get your own שבח. shevach. Yes, James. So just the בכור
bechor case, let's say there's four portions in the field, three brothers.
Yes, the בכור bechor gets two portions, each other brother gets one.
So the estate improves to every share is one and a half
now. Right. So the בכור bechor just gets one and a half
and not three? Wait, one more time, give me the scenario. There's
four portions. How many brothers? Three. Okay, so four portions, right? At
the time of death. Are we dealing with the יבום yibum case
now? No, just the בכור bechor case. Okay, fine, yeah. Yeah. So
it's two, one, and one at the time of death. Right. And
then the estate improves to 50% more. Right. So now it's worth
six units. Right. So now he gets, so the בכור bechor gets,
so now he gets two plus, he gets two and a half.
Two and a half, so he doesn't get three. Wait, wait, so
the extra, it improved two units worth. No, improved 50% more. Right,
it was, it improved two units worth. So and that's divided by
three brothers. So it's two-thirds. So he gets two and two-thirds and
they each get one and a third. So the בכור Bechor is
gaining from the improvements in the field after the father died. That's
what I'm asking. בכור Bechor is gaining from... nevermind. It improved. It
was worth four and he was going to get two and they
were each going to get one. Now it improved two. So you
divide that into thirds. I'm sorry. So the בכור Bechor gets two
and a third and they each get one and a third. Did
I do the math right? It improved two. The בכור's Bechor portion
always stays. So the בכור Bechor gets two and two-thirds and they
each get one and two-thirds. Right. At the time of death he
would have had two, they would have one and one. Okay? Now
it improved two units. Okay? Those two units are divided equally by
all three of them. So he gets two and two-thirds, they get
one and two-thirds and one and two-thirds. So basically what we were
saying before is it's not like the בכור Bechor doesn't get anything
out of that. He just doesn't get a double portion of that.
Yeah, he gets his own. Right. If this is, if the estate
is worth four, right? The estate is worth four. Right. Okay, so
A, B, well, whatever. A, A, B, C. Okay. A's the בכור,
Bechor, right? It's worth four units. Then after he dies it improves
two units. Okay. Those two units are divided equally into two-thirds, two-thirds,
two-thirds, and they're distributed equally. Okay. So he is an equal brother
in the שבח. shevach. He doesn't get פי שנים pi shenayim in
the שבח. shevach. Any improvements are divided equally among all the brothers.
Any improvements are divided equally among the brothers. Okay. All right. וכולם
אין נוטלין בשבח. Vekhulam ein notlin beshevach. Now it repeats that line.
Let's see if we can finish this. Okay, the rest of the
גמרא Gemara goes relatively quickly. Right, so why does it repeat that
they don't get the שבח? shevach? לעשויי שבחא דממילא. Le'asuyei shevcha demimeila.
Because even if it's improvement that happened naturally, like and it's not
through investments in the field, and then you might say that, oh,
it's natural, so I'm entitled to two portions, that's just a natural
improvement, so maybe I do get it? No. What would be an
example about that? חפורה והוו שבלי. Chafura vehavu shivli. Let's say they
were, it was basically like, it was the grain was was not
yet, had not yet, what's it called, like when it's just the
stalks, without the- it was just the stalks and then it actually
became laden with the grain. Okay? שלפופי והוי תמרי. Shalfufi vehavei tamrei.
Or the fruit on the tree was, you know, that you can
easily imagine, right? Because it's just let's say it rains, it's not
irrigated, it just naturally they come from being unripe and just beginning
to blossom to become- it actually became full dates. Okay? So even
though it's natural improvements, the בכור Bechor still does not get it.
Okay? And none of these people get it. Again, beyond their own
portion. They don't get their additional, or the כתובה ketubah they don't
get it at all. ולא בראוי כבמוחזק. Velo berauy kemuchzak. What's that
including? לאיתויי נכסי דאבא דאבא. Le'atuyei nichsei de'abba de'abba. Not only some
un- some type of a thing which maybe wouldn't have been expected
like getting an inheritance from a long-lost uncle, but even getting an
inheritance from their grandfather, their father's father, which you knew it was
coming, right? No matter what would happen, eventually the grandfather was going
to die and they and as they were the grandsons, they were
definitely going to get a portion of the estate. So even though
it was definite and it was a natural type of a thing,
since it wasn't in the estate at the time of death, you
do not- the בכור Bechor doesn't get a double portion. Okay? Let's
take a look now at the next משנה. mishnah. ואלו שאין חוזרין
ביובל. Ve'elu she'ein chozrin beyovel. Now that we're talking about בכור, Bechor,
this is, as we saw before, בכור Bechor was only one of
a list, so here too בכור Bechor will be one of a
list of special laws. Things that do not go back in the
יובל. Yovel. Okay, meaning, here's the story, right? We divided the estate,
I get a double portion, my brothers don't, or whatever, then the
יובל Yovel comes. Now, we're assuming that what we got as straight
inheritance obviously doesn't go back, we didn't purchase it. The idea of
יובל Yovel going back is when they were purchased, not inherited. Although
we'll see about that in the גמרא. Gemara. But maybe if I
got a double portion, maybe that should be just seen as like
a- as a בכור, Bechor, that extra portion should be seen as
a bonus and not as a real inheritance. And therefore maybe it
should go back to the father's estate at the יובל Yovel and
maybe be re-divided afterwards. Okay. So, which basically means you only have
a double portion till יובל Yovel and then maybe not? Maybe. But
חז"ל Chazal tell you not that way. Okay. Now we'll see other
opinions in the- other opinions. So the בכור Bechor does not go
back in the יובל. Yovel. והיורש את אשתו. Vehayoresh et ishto. If
somebody inherits his wife. A wife dies. So in the תורה Torah
it never is clear that a husband inherits his wife. חז"ל Chazal
say it's... Question whether whether that's biblical or rabbinic. The גמרא Gemara
itself questions whether that's biblical or rabbinic. So you might say if
it's only rabbinic, then he's not a real heir, he just- so
חז"ל Chazal maybe transferred ownership but still if he just transferred ownership
and he's not a real heir, that should go back to his
wife's family in the יובל. Yovel. No, it's not true, it doesn't
go back. והמיבם את אשת אחיו. Vehamyabem et eshet achiv. Somebody who
did יבום. yibum. He gets... את אשת אחיו, et eshet achiv, so
we just learned that he gets an extra portion. Again, that portion
is like an inheritance and it does not go back. והמתנה, V'hamatana,
and not only cases of inheritance or quasi-inheritance, but gifts, only sales
go back. דברי רבי מאיר, Divei Rabbi Meir, that's what רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says. וחכמים אומרים, Vachachamim omrim, the sages say, המתנה כמכר.
hamatana kemacher. No, they disagree, inheritance we grant you, but gifts, that's
like sale, that's basically taking it out of the natural lines of
the way, you know, things pass down, that's diverting it. So even
though it's not a sale, that goes back, which obviously makes sense.
Yes, just a straight gift to somebody. Okay, רבי אליעזר אומר, כולם
חוזרין ביובל, Rabbi Eliezer omer kulam chozrin beyovel. all of them go
back, even the בכור, bechor, even the יבום, yibum, those are not
real pure inheritance, everything goes back. Hard to measure, yep. Now the
question that, right, רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא אומר, Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka
omer, רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka says, היורש את
אשתו יחזיר לבני משפחה וינכה מן הדמים. hayoresh et ishto yachazir livnei
mishpacha veyinachem min hadamim. If somebody inherits from his wife and then
the יובל yovel comes, you give it back to the wife's family,
but they have to pay you for it. But you get to
deduct, but they don't pay you the full amount. So first of
all, the גמרא Gemara says, make up your mind. If it goes
back, then it's because of laws of יובל, yovel, they don't pay
you. If they pay you, then why are you telling me you
have to give it back? And what does this mean, deduct the
amount, some amount? So we'll talk about it in the גמרא. Gemara.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. מאי טעמא דרבי מאיר,
Mai ta'ama deRabbi Meir, what's the reason of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
that says none of this goes back? מכר הוא דאמר רחמנא ליהדר,
Mecher hu de'amar rachmana lehadar, it says only sales should go back
ביובל, beyovel, מתנה וירושה לא, matana veyerusha lo, nothing that isn't a
sale, even if it gets diverted, even if it's certainly not a
ירושה, yerusha, but not even a gift. והני מירושה ירושה דמתנה מתנה,
Vehani miyerusha yerusha, dematana matana, everything that's straight inheritance was inheritance, a
gift is a gift. Now let's look about the more slightly more
obscure cases. בכור, Bechor, so what's how do you define a בכור?
bechor? So לתת לו פי שנים, latet lo pi shenayim, מתנה קרייה
רחמנא, matana karyei rachmana, you don't even have to call בכור bechor
an inheritance. Once you say a gift doesn't go back, so it
says he's given, לתת לו, latet lo, he's given it, fine, call
it a gift, gifts don't go back either according to רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. היורש את אשתו, Hayoresh et ishto, ירושת הבעל דאורייתא. yerusha
deba'al de'oraita. Now you could have maybe also said that was a
gift דחז"ל deChazal gave him, but whatever, but it says no, we'll
call that a ירושה, yerusha, the husband inherits his wife, that's biblical.
והמיבם את אשת אחיו, Vehamayabem et eshet achiv, what? Biblical or rabbinic,
you said the husband? No, it's debated. So here we're saying that
to explain why it doesn't go back in the יובל, yovel, we're
calling it, we're saying that he holds the position that it's biblical.
Okay, it's interesting why the גמרא Gemara didn't call it מתנה, matana,
maybe because it felt that there was an element of exchange there,
that the reason he's entitled to inherit his wife is because of
other ways in which he supports his wife and therefore didn't want
to call it straight מתנה. matana. Okay, so a, so but calls
it ירושה. yerusha. According to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, you could either
call it ירושה yerusha or מתנה matana and it won't go back.
Okay, והמיבם את אשת אחיו, vehamayabem et eshet achiv, the guy who
does יבום, yibum, בכור קרייה רחמנא, bechor karyei rachmana, he's called a
בכור bechor like we saw on the first עמוד, amud, and that's
where we're saying is at least a מתנה, matana, so therefore it
doesn't go back. וחכמים אומרים המתנה כמכר, Vachachamim omrim hamatana kemacher, now
וחכמים vachachamim it's going to be harder because they reject מתנה, matana,
they say מתנה matana does go back, only ירושה yerusha is saved.
So they're going to have to call everything that does not go
back a type of a ירושה. yerusha. And now we'll go through
it. מאי טעמייהו דרבנן, Mai ta'amai deRabbanan, first what's the reasoning that
they say מתנה matana does go back? תשובו, Tashuvu, you shall return,
לרבות את המתנה. lerabbot et hamatana. The extra word of תשובו tashuvu
is coming to say not only cases of sale which are being
talked, but even gifts go back. Why did they get that? From
the extra word. והני כולהו ירושה נינהו, Vehani kulhu yerusha ninhu, so
these things that are excluded, we'll have to call them all a
ירושה. yerusha. בכור, Bechor, אמר קרא לתת לו פי שנים, amar kra
latet lo pi shenayim, to give him a double portion. So it
says double portion, it treats his extra portion like his original portion.
מקיש חלק בכור לחלק פשוט, Makish chelek bechor lechelek pashut, the extra's
like the basic one. מה חלק פשוט ירושה אף חלק בכור ירושה,
Ma chelek pashut yerusha, af chelek bechor yerusha, the same way the
base portion is inheritance, even the בכור, bechor, although it's limited, he
doesn't get, and although he doesn't get the improvements afterwards, nevertheless it's
a type of a ירושה. yerusha. So therefore we're going to have
to call everything a type of a ירושה. yerusha. בכור Bechor is
a type of a ירושה, yerusha, the, we're not going through the
other cases, but obviously he would say the wife is דאורייתא, de'oraita,
a type of a ירושה, yerusha, and the יבום yibum is a
בכור, bechor, so it's also a type of a ירושה. yerusha. Everything
is a type of a ירושה. yerusha. Okay, רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi
Eliezer omer, כולם חוזרין ביובל. kulam chozrin beyovel, So he obviously rejects,
says מתנה matana goes back, and now he's going to have to
say that none of the things we said constitute ירושה, yerusha, because
obviously ירושה yerusha doesn't go back, but none of these things constitute
ירושה. yerusha. סבר לה כרבנן דאמרי תשובו לרבות את המתנה, Savar lah
keRabbanan de'amri tashuvu lerabbot et hamatana, so number one gifts go back,
and he holds like the rabbis that learn it from תשובו. tashuvu.
והני כולהו מתנה נינהו, Vehani kulhu matana ninhu, these are all gifts.
בכור, Bechor, how do you know בכור bechor is considered a gift
not ירושה? yerusha? לתת לו פי שנים, Latet lo pi shenayim, to
give him, it's a gift. מתנה קרייה רחמנא, Matana karyei rachmana, it's
called a gift. היורש את אשתו, Hayoresh et ishto, ירושת הבעל דרבנן,
yerusha deba'al derabbanan, that's rabbinic, so that's not a, that's not a
ירושה, yerusha, what do you call it, a gift or מכר, mecher,
it's not a ירושה דאורייתא. yerusha de'oraita. והמיבם את אשת אחיו, Vehamayabem
et eshet achiv, the guy who does יבום, yibum, בכור קרייה רחמנא,
bechor karyei rachmana, because he's a type of a בכור. bechor. So
here you have in addition to the יובל yovel question, fascinating two
conceptual questions. Number one, when the בכור... bechor... Okay, there are limits
to it, לאו בראוי כבמוחזק, lav b'raui k'bemuchzak, does that tell you
it's not a ירושה Yerusha or not? So number one is the
בכור Bechor ירושה. Yerusha. Number two, when the מיבם Meyabem gets a
double portion, we've already said, is he getting a double portion like
a בכור, Bechor, or is he getting a double portion because he's
representing his brother? That also, although the גמרא Gemara here plays with
the בכור Bechor thing more, that also could conceptually tell you how
much is it a gift, how much is it a type of
a ירושה, Yerusha, and so on. So very interesting conceptual questions about
how you think about the ייבום's Yibbum double portion and how you
think about the בכור's Bechor double portion. Now, wait, wait, didn't we
have a... I guess we're going to get to this, but don't
we have what's this מחלוקת machlokes between brothers in general, אחים שחלקו?
achim shechalaku? Thank you, we're going to... that's the last סוגיא. sugya.
Okay, אמר רבי אסי אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Assi amar Rabbi
Yochanan, האחים שחלקו. ha'achim shechalaku. So now he's saying, okay, you're telling
me everybody forget the normal case, or forget בכור Bechor and everything,
normal ירושה Yerusha doesn't go back. But now we say in the
name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, but one minute, when they divide
the estate, is that considered that the portion that they go home
with, is that considered ירושה Yerusha or is that considered like they
bought their brother out? And if it's considered like they bought their
brother out, anybody who's divided an estate ultimately is a לקוח, lakoach,
not a יורש, yoresh, and it should all have to go back
and be re-divided at the time of the יובל. Yovel. Okay? So
he said האחים שחלקו לקוחות הן, ha'achim shechalaku lakochot hen, they are
actually purchasers, ומחזירין זה לזה ביובל. umachzirin zeh lazeh b'Yovel. They have
to... everything go back and be re-divided. Now you'll say, well, if
it's going to get re-divided afterwards, who cares? No, it's a big
care, because let's say on your portion of the estate we found
oil, and on my portion we didn't. So now it all goes
back and we re-divide, we all get to split up the new
estate that equally, even your portion with the oil on it. So
therefore he says it's all about purchase and it all goes back.
Now תוספות Tosafot says, even if your general position is they're like
a purchaser, you're still a purchaser in the context of ירושה. Yerusha.
This is the natural way ירושה Yerusha works. So there are many
people who would hold that an heir who divides the estate is
like a purchaser and would not say it goes back in the
יובל. Yovel. It's still in the context of how ירושה Yerusha operates.
It's only רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan that takes it to the extreme
conclusion that it now all goes back in the יובל. Yovel. And
that leads to obvious questions in the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this: מותיב רב הושעיא, Motiv Rav Hoshaia, רב הושעיא
Rav Hoshaia asked, ואלו שאין חוזרין ביובל, v'eilu she'ein chozrin b'Yovel, the
following do not go back in the יובל: Yovel: הבכורה. habechora. So
it says the בכורה bechora doesn't go back. Okay, so if the
בכורה bechora doesn't, certainly the primary, and even those that debate only
debate the בכורה, bechora, they don't debate the primary thing. So אמר
ליה רבי אלעזר, amar lei Rabbi Elazar, רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar says,
מאי אין חוזרין, mai ein chozrin, what does it mean the בכור
Bechor doesn't go back? אין חוזרין לבטלה. ein chozrin l'vatala. It means
that the בכור Bechor thing does not go back to be annulled.
Meaning, yes, it does go back during the יובל, Yovel, and they
share it equally during the יובל Yovel year, and then after the
יובל, Yovel, he retakes it. Okay? That's what... so but so it
means it's not annulled, but actually it does go back. And what
does that mean, they have it for יובל, Yovel, they can't do
anything with it? What does it mean they have it for יובל,
Yovel, they can't do anything with it? Yeah, but well first of
all again, necessarily, I mean let's say it's... let's say it's got
oil on it or something, let's say it's got diamonds in a
mine or who knows what. Mine all the diamonds and it has
to go back to your brother? Basically. Okay, anyway, so it means
that... then doesn't the בכור Bechor get his double portion back again
after יובל? Yovel? Yes, yes. So אין חוזרין לבטלה, ein chozrin l'vatala,
but... okay, so... so... so that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to...
so that's what it means. So the בכור Bechor does not go
back to be... for... for... for that it would get annulled. It
goes back, but then he takes it back afterwards. And the same
would be about the brothers. It goes back and they take it
back. But the difference would be... not necessarily, I don't think so.
That... that I think is the major difference, that the brothers it
goes back and then they re-divide it. Okay, that actually maybe... so
maybe even the בכור, Bechor, maybe he re-divides and his portion once
the value is different, you do a whole re-חשבון. cheshbon. So he
doesn't lose his בכורה, bechora, but it does go back during the
יובל. Yovel. מתקיף לה רב ששת, Matkif lah Rav Sheshet, so רב
ששת Rav Sheshet asks on this, מכלל דמאן דאמר חוזרין חוזרין לבטלה
קאמר? michlal d'man d'amar chozrin chozrin l'vatala ka'amar? So how about the
position that says the בכור Bechor portion goes back? Okay, I mean,
would you say that that means that after the יובל Yovel he
doesn't get his בכור Bechor portion? How can you say such a
thing? Right? Meaning, until now we assumed the question was whether it
ever gets, goes back to the primary estate. But of course even
if you said it goes back to the primary estate, after the
יובל Yovel you get... you take your portion back out. But now
we're saying no, no, no, everybody says it all goes to the
primary estate and... but after the יובל Yovel you re-divide. So the
position about בכור Bechor that says it's like back to the ירושה
Yerusha says he gets his double portion once they re-divide after the
יובל. Yovel. So are you going to say that there's somebody who
says that after the יובל Yovel the בכור Bechor doesn't walk away
with his double portion? So he says, so they say one person's
reductio ad absurdum is another person's אי הכי נמי. ee hachi nami.
So he says, אמר ליה, amar lei, so... so... one minute, so...
so... קרי רבי חמא עליה דרב ששת, kari Rabbi Chama aleih d'Rav
Sheshet, so רבי חמא Rabbi Chama said about רב ששת, Rav Sheshet,
טובה חכמה עם נחלה. tovah chochmah im nachalah. It's good... good is
wisdom with inheritance. Obviously, it's a play on inheritance. Inheritance, you inherit
stuff, you want to be wise about how you use your estate.
The reason he said this is רב ששת Rav Sheshet had a
lot of inheritance in the sense of he knew he was a
master of ברייתות. baraitot. He was a master of received tradition. So
we said a little bit of intelligence here or wisdom I should
say would be helpful because you asked something to you was like
it was absurd to suggest this. Actually that is what we say.
ולא שמיע ליה הא דכי יתיב רבין אמר רבי יוחנן ואמרי לה
רבי אלעזר אמר רבי שמעון בן אלעזר מאי חוזים חוזים לבטלה V'lo
shmiyah lei? Ha de-chi yasiv Ravin amar Rabbi Yochanan v'amrei lei Rabbi
Elazar amar Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar, Mai Chozim? Chozim l'batlah! Yes, you
were so astounded, how can anybody say such a thing? Okay, but
actually there are, that is a possibility. So if you say that
heirs always go back, so then when we say here that these
things don't, that these things what makes בכור bechor special if we
say that it goes back? So what makes בכור bechor ייבום yibum
whatever special would mean according to this that they lose after the
יובל yovel they've lost their extra portion. Okay? So, you got it?
Meaning the simple explanation is heirs don't go back and the only
question is do these revert at the יובל? yovel? Okay, and then
they'd be taken back out presumably afterwards, or maybe not. But anyway,
does it revert at the יובל? yovel? Now we're saying everybody reverts
at the יובל. yovel. It's just that the heirs get redistributed and
the question about the בכור bechor is does the בכור bechor also
does he take his portion back out or does he lose his
portion after the יובל? yovel? That's how it's explained according to רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan but again that's only רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan very
extreme position that's because even in the context of ירושה yerusha there's
an element of not just is there an element of purchase but
that's so significant that it would get it would get reverted it
would revert at the time of the יובל yovel and be redistributed
afterwards. Okay let's finish up the גמרא, Gemara, I know it's already
8:30 but let's just give it a few more minutes. רבי יוחנן
בן ברוקא אומר היורש את אשתו יחזיר לבני משפחה. Rabbi Yochanan ben
Beroka omer hayoresh et ishto yachazir livnei mishpacha. So a man who
inherits his wife he gives it back to the family but they
have to pay him. So מאי קסבר? mai kasavar? What does he
hold? אי קסבר ירושת הבעל דאורייתא I kasavar yerushat habaal d'oraita if
he holds that he was an heir biblically so אמאי יחזיר לבני
משפחה amai yachazir livnei mishpacha why does he have to give it
back on the יובל? yovel? ואי קסבר ירושת הבעל דרבנן V'i kasavar
yerushat habaal d'rabbanan if it's rabbinic דמים מאי עבידתייהו? damim mai avidat'hu?
Why are they paying him? לעולם קסבר ירושת הבעל דאורייתא. L'olam kasavar
yerushat habaal d'oraita. Yes it is biblical. So why is he giving
it back? הכא במאי עסקינן כגון שירשה אשתו בית קברות. Hacha b'mai
askinan kegon sheyarsha ishto beit kvarot. Let's say his wife actually had
in her as property not only her own grave but she actually
had a family gravesite and you know particularly in ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael you know they had these catacombs and right they had these
whole family plots. So she actually she was a Klein she married
I don't know a Smith whatever anyway a כהן Cohen anyway so
the Klein family plot was over in בית שמש Beit Shemesh right
her husband was a כהן Cohen and he lived in who knows
in אילת. Eilat. Okay so now he's going to inherit her and
have a portion in the Klein family plot you know which is
all with the Kleins and it's you know and it's totally invading
their family plot. So in that special case although he really is
entitled to it ומשום פגם משפחה אמרו רבנן לשקול דמי v'mishum pgam
mishpacha amru rabanan lishkol damei for the sake of because of the
concern of the of the sort of of the injury that's not
a good word here the I don't know פגם pgam is not
a physical injury but somehow the stain on the family that they
actually are losing a portion of their family plot either entirely or
partially okay because of that concern about that stigma אמרו רבנן לשקול
דמי ולהדר amru rabanan lishkol damei v'lihader so they instituted that at
least at the יובל yovel you might have said maybe automatically it
have to be that way if he inherits the family plot okay
but this at least is sounding that well actually I should take
that back because it's probably רבי יוחנן בן Rabbi Yochanan ben it
sounds like it's not clear you know whether originally the גמרא Gemara
interpreted רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka in the context
of the יובל. yovel. Now that we're saying it's a special institution
for the family's honor it's not clear why it should be limited
to the יובל yovel okay but at least גמרא Gemara initially thought
it was in that context so whether it's limited to that is
not clear but anyway they say that yes give it back לשקול
דמי ולהדר lishkol damei v'lihader take the money and give it back
וכי תניא v'chi tanya like we taught in the ברייתא Baraita so
what happened so he so he inherits his wife now he's got
a portion in the Klein family plot or maybe he's even has
more than one portion maybe he's got a whole major cat set
of catacombs there okay that is a you know a stain on
their honor that this stranger has a portion in their plot and
other people are going to be buried in their plot not not
part of the family so therefore they say we're forcing him to
sell it back to them okay even now וכי תניא v'chi tanya
like we taught in the ברייתא Baraita המוכר קברו ודרך קברו hamocher
kvuro v'derech kvuro if somebody sells from his family plot he sells
his plot to somebody else to a total stranger and the pathway
to his plot in the middle of a whole family section מקום
מעמדו makom amado and the place where they would do the מעמדות
mamadot that the people would stand to consult ובית הספד u'beit hesped
where they would do the eulogies he sold that his portion in
the middle of a whole larger family plot באים בני משפחה וקוברים
אותו על כרחו baei bnei mishpacha v'kovrin oto al korcho they come
and they bury him in his in his plot. even though somebody
else now owns it משום פגם משפחה *mishum pgam mishpacha* because of
the affront to the family honor. They would presumably pay the guy
back for it, but they are entitled to reseize the plot. And
now we seem to be very much out of the יובל *Yovel*
context. So there you flagrantly violated, here the woman just died, but
it doesn't matter, it's not because of the person's offense, it's because
of the honor of the family. They're entitled to retake the plot
and then they pay him for it. Now, ומה ינכה להם מן
הדמים *u'mah yenakeh lahem min hadamim*, what does it mean he reduces
the money? דמי קבר אשתו *d'mei kever ishto*, it means he's obligated
to bury his wife. So now, let's say the plot was worth
ten thousand dollars. They give him ten thousand dollars back. But now
his wife is obviously going to be buried over there with the
clans, right? They want their whole family there. So they're paying now,
because if they pay for the whole ten thousand dollars, they're paying
for her plot amongst that whole section. So now what he charges
them, ten thousand minus the cost of his wife's section, because it
was his financial responsibility to pay for his wife's burial anyway. So
if there were ten plots there and they paid him ten thousand,
they really only pay him nine, because he's got his financial responsibility
to bury his wife even though now she's going to be buried
over there with the clans. So does that ever work? That the
wife would never get buried in the husband's plot? Not never, this
is in a case where there was a family plot and they
were not ready to bury even their married daughters there. Okay, it
all goes back to that. But anyway, we had some fascinating discussion
here at the end about בכור *bechor* conceptually, besides the whole יובל
*Yovel* issue about רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, the question about whether the
בכור *bechor*'s extra portion is a gift or an inheritance, and whether
the יבם *yavam*'s extra portion is representing his dead brother or is
it itself a type of בכור *bechor*. And tomorrow, beginning tomorrow, we
begin a new פרק *perek* and a totally new topic.